I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we examine the
sketchy supplement industry.
And by sketchy,
I don’t mean artistic.
In our first story,
we take a close look
at the industry’s attempts
to rebut an editorial
in an alternative
medicine journal.
An editorial was recently published decrying
much of the multibillion dollar marketing
of dietary supplements in North America as
misleading, deceptive — even predatory.
After examining hundreds of sales claims
made when supplements are being marketed
over the years, the author concluded:
"Dishonesty or wild exaggerations are
frequent occurrences in the
marketing of supplements."
My favorite quote was: "The marketers
of supplements like to use scientific
evidence the way a drunk uses a lamp-post:
more for support than illumination."
This is nothing new.
Similar editorials have been published
in the Journal of the American Medical
Association and the New England
Journal of Medicine.
What made this special was that it was,
to their credit, published in
the Journal of Alternative and
Complementary Medicine.
It’s like their own journal admitting it!
In response, the Head of Global Supplement
Initiatives at Novus, which actually
started out as the livestock feed
additives division of Monsanto, before
branching off into human feed additives —
dietary supplements — starts his rebuttal
with this counterpoint: "In his review
entitled ’The Marketing of Dietary
Supplements in North America: The Emperor
is (Almost) Naked,’ [the author] may be
mortified to know the emperor is still
dancing in the street, dressed or not,
to the tune of $68 billion.
This figure is much higher and is a more
relevant number than cited… indicating
a very strong and respectable commerce."
That’s his first argument?
That it’s highly lucrative?
He goes on to say that hey, they’re
safer than some pharmaceuticals.
But how much is that saying, given that
prescription drugs kill an estimated
106,000 Americans every year?
And that’s not errors;
not abuse; not overdose.
That’s just deaths from side effects,
ADRs (adverse drug reactions), which
would make doctors — me and my fellow
colleagues — the fourth leading cause
of death in the United States.
So, for the supplement industry to say,
"Hey, at least we’re not the fourth
leading cause of death,"
isn’t saying much.
Next up, calcium supplements.
Might they increase the
risk of heart attacks?
Here’s the story.
In 12 short years, government panels
have gone from suggesting widespread
calcium supplementation may be
necessary to protect our bones to
"Do Not Supplement."
What happened?
It all started with a 2008
study in New Zealand.
Short-term studies had showed that
calcium supplementation may drop
blood pressures by about a point,
though the effect appears transient,
disappearing after a few months,
but it's better than nothing.
And excess calcium in the gut
can cause fat malabsorption,
by forming soap fat, reducing
saturated fat absorption
and increasing fecal
saturated fat content.
And indeed if you take eat a couple Tums
along with your half bucket of KFC,
up to twice as much fat
could end up in your stool.
And with less saturated fat absorbed in
your system your cholesterol might drop.
So the New Zealand researchers were
expecting to lower heart attack rates
by giving women calcium supplements.
To their surprise there appeared
to be more heart attacks
in the calcium supplement
group. Was this just a fluke?
All eyes turned to the Women's
Health Initiative, the largest and
longest randomized controlled trial
of calcium supplementation.
The name might sound familiar.
That's the study that uncovered
how dangerous hormone
replacement therapy was.
Would it do the same for
calcium supplements?
The Women's Health Initiative
reported no adverse effects.
However, the majority
of the participants
were already taking calcium
supplements before the study started,
so effectively the study was
just comparing higher versus
lower dose calcium supplementation,
not calcium supplements versus
no calcium supplements.
But what if you go back and just
see what happened to the women
who started out not taking supplements
and then were randomized
to the supplement group?
Those who started calcium
supplements suffered significantly
more heart attacks or strokes.
Thus, high dose or low dose, any
calcium supplementation seems
to increase cardiovascular
disease risk.
So researchers went back digging
through other trial data for heart attack
and stroke rates in women
randomized to calcium supplements,
with or without vitamin D added,
and confirmed the danger.
And most of the population
studies agreed:
users of calcium supplements
tended to have increased rates
of heart disease, stroke, and death.
The supplement industry
was not happy,
accusing the researchers
of relying in part
on self-reported data -- like they just
ask if people had a heart attack or not
rather than verifying it.
And indeed long-term
calcium supplementation
causes all sorts of
gastrointestinal distress
including twice the risk of being
hospitalized with acute symptoms
that may have been confused
with a heart attack.
But no, the increased risk
was seen consistently
across the trials whether the
heart attacks were verified or not.
OK, but why do calcium supplements
increase heart attack risk,
but not calcium you get in your diet?
Perhaps because when
you take calcium pills,
you get a spike of calcium
in your bloodstream
that you don't get just
eating calcium rich foods.
Within hours of taking supplemental
calcium, the calcium levels
in the blood shoot up and can
stay up as long as eight hours.
This evidently produces what's called a
hypercoaguable state -- your blood clots
more easily -- which could increase
the risk of clots in the heart and brain.
And indeed higher
calcium blood levels
are tied to higher heart
attack and stroke rates.
So the mechanism may
be calcium supplements
leading to unnaturally large, rapid, and
sustained calcium levels in the blood,
which can have a variety
of potentially problematic effects.
Calcium supplements have been
widely embraced on the grounds that
they are a natural and therefore a safe
way of preventing osteoporotic fractures.
But it's now becoming clear that taking
calcium in one or two daily doses
is not natural, in that it does not
reproduce the same metabolic effects
as calcium in food --
the way nature intended.
And furthermore the evidence is
also becoming steadily stronger
that calcium supplementation
may not be safe.
That's why most organizations
providing advice regarding bone health
now recommend that individuals
should obtain their calcium requirement
from diet in preference to supplements.
Finally today, black raspberry
supplements are put to the test.
The regulation of dietary supplements
in the United States
has been described as
too little, too late.
Dietary supplements
may be adulterated
with dangerous compounds,
be contaminated,
fail to contain what
they say they contain,
contain unknown doses
of the ingredients
listed on
the label,
be sold at
toxic dosages,
or produce harmful
effects in other ways.
This not only messes up any
research done on them,
but can put the
general public at risk.
A third party company
that has tested
thousands of supplements,
identified approximately
1 in 4 with a quality problem,
either not containing
what it says
or contaminated
in some way – 1 in 4.
For example, I’ve
done a few videos
on the remarkable properties
of black raspberries.
Can’t always find
them fresh or frozen;
so how about black
raspberry supplements?
You go to the store
or look online.
How about this one?
Fresh, raw, pure—
that sounds good.
Let’s look at the back.
It says it contains just seedless
black raspberry powder
and absolutely nothing else –
exclamation point!
It’s nice to see
there are no fillers
or artificial
ingredients.
So, you plunk
down your $23.77,
but it turns out
you’ve been had.
The first clue was
that the picture
on the front was actually
blackberries photoshopped
to look like black
raspberries—
they couldn’t even be bothered
to put a real image
on their fake supplement.
The researchers' second clue
was that it sure didn’t look
like pure black
raspberry powder;
and so, they put
it to the test,
and indeed, there was no
black raspberry at all.
Instead of absolutely
nothing else,
they should have just
stopped with
"This bottle contains
absolutely nothing!".
Or, at least you hope
it contains nothing—
who knows what’s actually
in those capsules.
They tested every black raspberry
product they could find,
and even ones with the
right picture on the front
and powder that
actually looked real,
yet more than a third
appeared to have
no black raspberry
fruit at all.
At the moment,
a consumer who assumes
the US dietary supplement
marketplace is free from risk
or even honest is
unfortunately naive.
How widespread is
this deception?
Researchers used DNA
fingerprinting techniques
to test the authenticity
of 44 herbal supplements
from a dozen different
companies.
Less than half of the
supplements were authentic,
containing what they
said they did.
Most contained plants
not listed on the label,
substitutions with
cheaper plants,
contaminants, unlisted fillers,
or apparently all filler.
And this isn’t
just fraud;
some of this deception
can really hurt people.
For example, one St. John’s
wort supplement
had no St. John’s
wort at all,
but actually contained
Senna instead,
which is an
herbal laxative
that can cause
adverse effects,
such as chronic diarrhea, liver damage,
skin breakdown, and blistering.
Until dietary supplements in
the U.S. are better regulated
and quality control standards
are defined and endorsed,
the safer source of
phytonutrients
as a consumer is
from actual food.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.